<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts | Gabriel De La Rosa</title>
    <link>/post/</link>
      <atom:link href="/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Posts</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/icon_hu0b7a4cb9992c9ac0e91bd28ffd38dd00_9727_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_2.png</url>
      <title>Posts</title>
      <link>/post/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>When we ski, we scare away alpine animals. That’s putting them at risk, scientists say.</title>
      <link>/post/lynx/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/lynx/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When we ski, we scare away alpine animals. That’s putting them at risk, scientists say.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gabriel De La Rosa&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This past New Year’s Day, I found myself shimmying my way uphill on touring skis, trying to keep up with a spry, acclimated group of friends. We were about an hour away from Boulder, Colorado, my newfound home. I had moved here to ski, to live near the towering alpine cirques and rolling slopes of the Rocky Mountains. And here I was, a few days in, fighting the effects of altitude for a bit of wintertime adrenaline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not once during our New Year’s ski did I consider how our group of skiers might be disrupting alpine species. Like many of my skiing friends, I assumed backcountry recreation was an ecologically benign activity. We practice “leave no trace” principles, travel in mostly small groups, and stick to established trails. We try to leave the places we visit just as we found them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, despite our best efforts to limit our impact, wintertime recreation does disturb alpine fauna. New research is finding that skiing and snowmobiling are much more disruptive to certain species than previously assumed. A new study, for example, finds Canada Lynx respond negatively to increasing numbers of skiers and snowmobilers in Southern Colorado.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To understand how backcountry travel affects lynx, researchers at the Rocky Mountain Research Station outfitted recreational snowmobilers and skiers with small GPS devices through winter. They tracked lynx using GPS collars, and mapped GPS data to look for overlap, or lack thereof, of lynx and winter recreationalists.
Researchers found that recreational backcountry travel, particularly snowmobiling, causes lynx to migrate out of otherwise suitable habitat. Habitat reduction can cause species numbers to decline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A new risk to lynx is particularly important: their Colorado population has only recently stabilized. In 1970, Lynx were pushed to local extinction in the Rocky Mountains by overtrapping and property development in alpine areas. Amazingly, an ambitious 1999 reintroduction effort resurrected the lynx population in Southern Colorado. But, snow sports are putting this “saved” species at risk once again.
Snowsports harm animals other than the lynx, too. Many bird populations are fragmented by skiing; their habitat is significantly reduced when mountains are turned into ski resorts. Male pine martens, a small rodent, see higher mortality near ski resorts than in the wild. Mammals, especially moose, expend unnecessary energy to avoid humans in the wilderness. Surprisingly, human powered recreation, like backcountry skiing, is more disturbing to fauna than backcountry motorsports like snowmobiling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The findings that lynx and other animals react negatively to snow sports illustrates an important point: as human populations grow in mountain regions, and more people venture farther and farther into pristine backcountry environments, we must understand and mitigate our effects on once undisturbed species.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing how wildlife responds to both urban and backcountry disturbance can help inform where public land managers decide to put infrastructure. In the backcountry, roads, trailheads, and snowmobile parks concentrate recreation to specific areas. Closer to town, ski resorts clear swaths of forest to accommodate groomed runs. New housing expands uphill and into once wild forest. New roads segment existing groves; old roads see more and more car traffic. Picking strategic locations for development can concentrate recreation to well defined areas and limit the spread of human impact on alpine environments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can keep skiing, and keep the lynx alive. But, we must be conscious of our impact on alpine wildlife. We must obey off limits areas and support managed access plans in wilderness areas. We can do this by listening to the research, and implementing science based management in wilderness areas. And, we must continue to leave no trace, to stick to established trails, and&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
